Guide to the Museum of Biblical Art Records 1997-2015 MS 3094
New-York Historical Society
Museum of Biblical Art records
1997-2015
New-York Historical Society
Museum of Biblical Art
MS 3094
30 Linear feet in 30 record cartons
(Note: Access to the collection is restricted until August 1, 2025.) The Museum of Biblical Art records include curatorial, administration, and exhibition files dating from its time as the Gallery at the American Bible Society in 1997 to its closing in 2015. MoBiA was founded in order to highlight the influence that the Bible has had on art while keeping a secular distance. The majority of the records relate the museums numerous exhibitions over the years including the checklists, condition reports, clippings, and loan agreements as well as other information. There are also documents regarding the administration of the museum and its continual relationship with the American Bible Society. MoBiA closed in 2015 following financial difficulties and its inability to find a new location in New York City.
Arrangement
This record group is organized into four series:
I. Administrative Files
II. Exhibition Files
III. Press Clippings
IV. Printed Materials
Historical Note
The Museum of Biblical Art (MoBiA) was an institution located in New York City that sought to remain religiously neutral while pursuing its key mission of providing insight into the ways that the Bible has influenced art. It was originally created as the Gallery at the American Bible Society in 1997 with Ena Heller placed as its director. It was not until 2005 that it officially became its own independent institution and was renamed as the Museum of Biblical Art. However, despite the fact that MoBiA was a separate institution from the American Bible Society (ABS), it continued to be located within the ABS headquarters and received a large majority of its funds from ABS as well.
Its first exhibition was "Coming Home! Self-Taught Artists, the Bible and the American South." Due to that fact that MoBiA did not house a permanent collection of its own, most of its exhibitions over the next decade required loans from other institutions and artists. Other exhibitions included "Biblical Art in a Secular Century," "Chagall's Bible," and "Louis C. Tiffany and the Art of Devotion." Such exhibitions included a broad range of works from several different regions and time periods. Its last exhibition was "Sculpture in the Age of Donatello: Renaissance Masterpieces from Florence Cathedral" which featured pieces that had never before been shown in the United States.
In 2015, the American Bible Society moved its headquarters from New York City to Philadelphia. Since MoBiA had previously been able to rent its location in ABS for a very minimal price, the museum now found it a challenge to find a new location that it would be able to afford. Therefore, by the summer of 2015, the Museum of Biblical Art officially closed due to financial constraints.
Access Restrictions
Under the terms of the gift agreement with the Museum of Biblical Art, access to the collection is restricted for a period of ten years, that is, until August 1, 2025. During this restricted period, access is permitted only with written permission from the donor's designated trustees. For further information, contact the N-YHS Library's Curator of Manuscripts at manuscripts@yhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift from Museum of Biblical Art in 2015.
Scope and Contents
The Museum of Biblical Art records include curatorial, administration, and exhibition files from 1997 to 2015. The documents concern MoBiA's time as an independent museum from 2005 to 2015 as well as its original status as the Gallery at the American Bible Society from 1997 to 2004.
Due to the fact that MoBiA had no permanent collections of its own, the majority of the files relate to the organization of exhibitions. These include loan agreements, checklists, and installation plans as well as other details regarding the realization of MoBiA's displays. The amount of records regarding each exhibition differs greatly, but the majority of the files include numerous documents concerning the acquisition of art works and their layout in the museum. The majority of the files pertain to exhibitions organized once MoBiA became its own institution, however, there are a few items that date back to its time as the Gallery at the American Bible Society. There are also records regarding the creation of books and symposiums to accompany some of the exhibitions.
In addition, the records include information related to the administration of MoBiA. There are agendas, minutes, and meeting notes from the decade long work of the Board of Trustees. These pertain to topics such as finances, programs, and the eventual dissolution of the board in 2015. Items also concern other administrative factors of MoBiA's such as financial, strategic, and operational planning. Although the museum was officially independent from the American Bible Society, MoBiA still received many donations from ABS and was located within their New York City headquarters. Therefore, there are also files related to the relationship between the two institutions. These include financial agreements as well as lease contracts. There are also records regarding meetings in which both MoBiA and ABS discuss what type of relationship they should have and how they should move forward with it.
Other materials include press clippings about both individual exhibitions and MoBiA in general as well as pamphlets, postcards, and brochures for each of the museum's exhibitions.
Art -- Exhibitions.; Art museums -- New York (State) -- New York.; Artists; Bible -- History of Biblical events -- Art.; Brochures.; Contracts.; Letters (correspondence); Financial records.; Minutes (administrative records); Museum loans; Postcards.; Press clippings.; Traveling exhibitions.; American Bible Society; American Bible Society. Gallery
- Series I. Administrative Files, 1997-2015; 6.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes records related to the administration of the Museum of Biblical Art (MoBiA). There are files related to the actions of the Board of Trustees. These include minutes and agendas of each meeting from 2005 to the dissolution of the Board in 2015. Such documents relate to MoBiA's finances and the goals for the future of the museum. There are also records of each individual member of the Board of Trustees, which include financial contributions and correspondence.
  In addition, there are several files that concern the relationship between MoBiA and the American Bible Society (ABS). These include lease agreements since MoBiA was located within the American Bible Society headquarters as well as financial agreements. There are also documents regarding the two institutions' different visions for the future of their relationship and how these differences progress over the years.
  Records pertaining to the other administrative aspects of the museum are also present. These related to MoBiA's committees which played a part in the planning of new exhibitions; the strategies that MoBiA should pursue to reach new audiences; the attempts to find a new location for the museum; and the financial goals for the institution. There are also miscellaneous reports, correspondence, and other documents related to other aspects of MoBiA's administration.
  Arrangement
  The container list of this series is roughly arranged by topic with documents related to higher ranking administrative bodies placed first. Duplicates are located at the end.
  - Board of Trustees, meetings (6 folders), 2005-2015 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-6)
  - Board of Trustees, members (4 folders), 2004-2015 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 7-10)
  - Board of Trustees, members, 2005-2015 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees, board retreat, 2011-2012 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 2)
  - American Bible Society relations (6 folders), 2000-2015 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3-8)
  - American Bible Society relations, 2011-2012 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 1)
  - Operational (4 folders), 2003-2015 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 9-12)
    Includes strategic plans, business plans, institutional plans, and operational plans.
  - Building Committee (2 folders), 2013-2014 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - Executive Committee, 2009-2015 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 3)
  - Exhibitions Committee (2 folders), 2011-2014 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 4-5)
  - Exhibitions Committee, 2011-2014 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 2)
    Includes list of MoBiA's exhibitions and their dates from 1998 to 2013.
  - Development Committee, 2013-2014 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6)
  - Financial reports (4 folders), 2006-2015 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 7-10)
  - Facilities, lease, 2006-2014 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 11)
  - Facilities, renovations, 2004-2006 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 12)
  - Facilities, design (3 folders), 1997-2000 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 6-8)
  - Facilities reports (2 folders), 1997-2011 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 9-10)
  - Correspondence (3 folders), 1999-2014 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 13-15)
  - Museum Policies, 2005 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1)
  - Museum Charter, 2004 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 3)
  - Governance manual, 2013-2014 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 2)
  - Communications Report, 2014-2015 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 3)
  - Audience development report, 2010 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 11)
  - Press coverage (4 folders), 2005-2012 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 4-7)
  - Miscellaneous (3 folders), 2010-2014 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 8-10)
  - Miscellaneous (4 folders), 1998-2015 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 4-7)
  - DVDs and CDs (3 folders) (RESTRICTED), 2000-2014 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 11-13)
    Includes CDs and DVDs. These are currently restricted from access in order to ensure that the digital files are not accidentally corrupted.
  - Operational (duplicates), 2003-2015 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1)
  - Press coverage (duplicates) (4 folders), 2005-2012 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2-5)
  - Additional Excess Copies, 1998-2015 (Offsite-box 30)
    This box holds excess copies of various documents found elsewhere in the collection.
- Series II. Exhibition Files, 1998-2015; 17.5 Linear feet
  This series includes records related to the planning and actualization of several exhibitions that the Museum of Biblical Art displayed. The majority of the files relate to exhibitions that were put on after MoBiA became its own organization in 2005. Therefore, there are relatively few records regarding exhibitions that were on display when it was the Gallery of the American Bible Society from 1997 to 2004. Nevertheless, the number of exhibitions following this period appears to be complete, as there are no gaps in the exhibitions until the museum closes in 2015.
  The amount of information regarding each exhibition varies in quantity. However, generally, most files will include the loan agreements, condition reports, checklists, exhibition contracts, shipping information, and climate reports for each exhibition. In addition, there may be label designs, research documents, wall layout plans, and installation strategies as well. There is also much correspondence related to the acquisition of certain works of art and the requests to other institutions for such pieces. If an exhibition travelled beyond its time at MoBiA, then there will be files pertaining to the planning and the condition reports related to that.
  Catalogues were prepared for some of the exhibitions that MoBiA organized and the files hold a copy of those. There are also records related to the development of the catalogue, including planning for works to be featured, the photos to be used, and the scholars that would participate in its publication. At times, there are also files regarding the organization of symposiums and lectures for an exhibition. If there are any unusual or significant additional items in the files, then these will be noted in the Scope and Content note at the folder level below.
  There are some exhibition files that include photographs, however, these are not of the actual exhibitions. Instead, the photos are largely included with condition reports in order to detail certain aspects of a piece for such reports.
  The series is arranged in chronological order, based on the opening dates of each exhibition. Exhibitions that travelled passed the original dates of their showing will be placed with the folders of the initial exhibition despite their being shown at a later time. If there are records of a travelling exhibition, then this will be noted in the Scope and Content note of the folders.
  Files are labelled by the official exhibition titles and the actual dates of the showings. Note that some of the exhibitions were subject to changes in both titles and dates over the course of their development. In addition, some of the actual folders in the records are labelled with abbreviated versions of the exhibition titles. Therefore, it is important to note that such information in the files may not completely match their description in the finding aid. In the case of the frequent use of a differing title or date, this distinction will be acknowledged in the Scope and Content note.
  - Rare Bible Collection, 1998 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 9)
  - Images in Procession: Testimonies to the Spanish Faith, 2000 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 10)
  - In Search of Mary Magdalene: Images and Traditions, 2002 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 11)
  - Icons or Portraits? Images of Jesus and Mary across the Centuries from the Collection of Michael Hall (7 folders), 2002 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 1-7)
    Includes photos of the pieces featured in the exhibition.
  - Reflections on Glass: 20th Century Stained Glass in American Art and Architecture, 2002 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 8)
  - Finding Faith: Folk Art of Peru from the Collection of Antonio Lulli (2 folders), 2003 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 9-10)
  - Coming Home! Self Taught Artists, the Bible, and the American South, 2005 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 1)
  - For Glory and for Beauty: Highlights from the Collection, 2005 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 2)
  - The Next Generation: Contemporary Expressions of Faith, 2005 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 3)
  - Let There Be Light: Oil-Lamps from the Holy Land (4 folders), 2005 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 4-7)
  - This Anguished World of Shadows: Georges Rouault's "Miserere et Guerre" (6 folders), 2006 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 8-13)
  - This Anguished World of Shadows: Georges Rouault's "Miserere et Guerre" (7 folders), 2006 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 1-7)
    Includes documents regarding the exhibition travelling to different venues during the years after its original showing at the Museum of Biblical Art.
  - The Word on the Street: The Photographs of Larry Racioppo (4 folders), 2006 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 8-11)
  - Gilded Legacies: The Saint John's Bible in Context (6 folders), 2006 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 1-6)
  - Biblical Art in a Secular Century: Selections, 1896-1993 (5 folders), 2006 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 7-11)
    Formerly titled "Minding Traditions? Twentieth Century Artists and the Judeo-Christian Legacy."
  - Biblical Art in a Secular Century: Selections, 1896-1993 (7 folders), 2006 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 1-7)
  - Ethiopian Art from the Walters Art Museum (5 folders), 2007 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 8-12)
  - The Christian Story: Five Asian Artists Today (4 folders), 2007 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 13-16)
    Previously titled "Biblical Art and the Asian Imagination."
  - The Christian Story: Five Asian Artists Today (6 folders), 2007 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 1-6)
  - The Art of Forgiveness: Images of the Prodigal Son (5 folders), 2007 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 7-11)
  - The Art of Forgiveness: Images of the Prodigal Son (9 folders), 2007 (Offsite-box 19, Box 1-9)
  - Before the Flame Goes Out: The Romaniote Jews in Ioannina and New York, 2008 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 10)
  - Realms of Faith: Medieval Art from the Walters Art Museum (11 folders), 2008 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 1-11)
    Includes documents related to a symposium held about the exhibition.
  - Albrecht Dürer: Art in Transition, 2008 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 12)
  - Florence Portfolio, 2008 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 13)
  - Chagall's Bible: Mystical Storytelling (6 folders), 2008 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 1-6)
    Includes records of the exhibition travelling to different museums after its original showing in the Museum of Biblical Art.
  - Transfluence, 2008 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 7)
  - Reel Religion: A Century of the Bible and Film (4 folders), 2009 (Offsite-box 21, Box 8-11)
  - Scripture for the Eyes: Bible Illustration in Netherlandish Prints of the Sixteenth Century (3 folders), 2009 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 12-14)
  - Scripture for the Eyes: Bible Illustration in Netherlandish Prints of the Sixteenth Century (4 folders), 2009 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 1-4)
  - Altered Religious Texts, 2009 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 5)
  - Tobi Kahn: Sacred Spaces for the 21st Century (5 folders), 2009 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 6-10)
  - Scripture, Image, Life: Orthodox Christianity (2 folders), 2009 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 11-12)
  - Uneasy Communion: Jews, Christians, and the Altarpieces of Medieval Spain (12 folders), 2010 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 1-12)
    Includes film of the exhibition pieces. Some documents are in Spanish.
  - Uneasy Communion: Jews, Christians, and the Altarpieces of Medieval Spain (4 folders), 2010 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 1-4)
    Includes records from the planning of a similar exhibition for the Jewish Museum titled "Jews and Art in Medieval Aragon" which was eventually cancelled.
  - The Glory of Ukraine: Sacred Images from the 11th to the 19th Centuries (4 folders), 2010 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 5-8)
  - The Wanderer: Foreign Landscapes of Enrique Martínez Celaya (4 folders), 2010 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 9-12)
    Formerly titled "The Stranger: A Biblical Reading of Enrique Martínez Celaya."
  - Passion in Venice: Crivelli to Tintoretto and Veronese (12 folders), 2011 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 1-12)
  - On Eagles' Wings: The King James Bible Turns 400 (3 folders), 2011 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 1-3)
  - The Land of Light and Promise: 50 Years Painting Jerusalem and Beyond, Ludwig Blum (6 folders), 2011 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 4-9)
  - Walls Speak: The Narrative of Hildreth Meière (2 folders), 2012 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 10-11)
  - The Adoration of the Magi by Bartolo di Fredi: A Masterpiece Reconstructed (3 folders), 2012 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 12-14)
  - Louis C. Tiffany and the Art of Devotion (8 folders), 2012 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 1-8)
    Includes grant proposals.
  - Ashe to Amen: African-Americans and Biblical Imagery (5 folders), 2013 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 9-13)
  - Ashe to Amen: African-Americans and Biblical Imagery (8 folders), 2013 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 1-8)
  - As Subject and Object: Contemporary Book Artists Explore Sacred Hebrew Texts (6 folders), 2013 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 9-14)
    Includes statements and biographies of some of the artists whose work is featured in the exhibition.
  - Sacred Visions: Nineteenth-Century Biblical Art from the Danesh Museum Collection (4 folders), 2013 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 1-4)
    Includes records of exhibition travelling to different venues after original showing at the Museum of Biblical Art.
  - Object of Devotion: Medieval English Alabaster Sculpture from the Victoria and Albert Museum (2 folders), 2014 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 5-6)
    Includes audio tour script.
  - Back to Eden: Contemporary Artists Wander the Garden (2 folders), 2014 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 7-8)
  - Dürer, Rembrandt, Tiepolo: The Jansma Master Prints Collection from the Grand Rapids Art Museum (2 folders), 2015 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 9-10)
  - Sculpture in the Age of Donatello: Renaissance Masterpieces from Florence Cathedral (4 folders), 2015 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 11-14)
    Includes some documents in Italian.
  - Sculpture in the Age of Donatello: Renaissance Masterpieces from Florence Cathedral (3 folders), 2015 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 1-3)
    Includes CD of audio tour and grant proposals.
  - Power and Piety: Spanish Colonial Art from the Colección Patricia Phelps de Cisneros, 2015 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 4)
    "Power and Piety" was not realized in the Museum of Biblical Art due to the fact that it closed shortly before the exhbition was due to begin. Therefore, the exhibition was shown in Palm Beach, Florida later in 2016.
- Series III. Press Clippings, 1998-2015; 4.5 Linear feet
  This series includes numerous press clippings regarding MoBiA's exhibitions and the museum in general. The clippings are organized into booklets depending on either their year of publication or their topic. From 2002 onwards, these booklets are increasingly organized by exhibition. It is important to note that before 2005, these clippings were usually divided into separate booklets as media logs and press clipping archives, but afterwards are organized into one booklet as a press clippings archive.
  The materials of this series are arranged in chronological order with duplicates placed at the end of the series.
  - Press clippings 1998-1999 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Media log, August 1998-May 2000, 1998-2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Press clippings, 2000-2001 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Media log, July 2000-August 2001, 2000-2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Media log, July 2001-September 2002, 2001-2002 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Press clippings, 2002-2003 (3 folders) (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8-10)
  - Press clippings, December 2002-March 2003, 2002-2003 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Media log, May 2003-September 2003 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Press clippings, 2003-2004 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Press clippings, May 12-July 24, 2005 (4 folders) (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Press clippings, August 20-November 13, 2005 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Press clippings, December 1, 2005-February 26, 2006, 2005-2006 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - Press clippings, 2005-2010 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - Press clippings, March 30-May 28, 2006 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - Press clippings, June 15-August 20, 2006 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
  - Press clippings, September 7-November 26, 2006 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
  - Press clippings, December 14, 2006-March 11, 2007, 2006-2007 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
  - Press clippings, March 22-May 20, 2007 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
  - Press clippings, June 8-September 16, 2007 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
  - Press clippings, October 14, 2007-February 17, 2008, 2007-2008 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
  - Press clippings, March 5-July 13, 2008 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
  - Press clippings, July 26-September 21, 2008 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - Press clippings, October 7, 2008-January 18, 2009, 2008-2009 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
  - Press clippings, February 6-May 17, 2009 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
    Includes DVD's from "Reel Religion: A Century of the Bible and Film" exhibition.
  - Press clippings, June 5-September 27, 2009 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
  - Press clippings, October 16, 2009-January 24, 2010, 2009-2010 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
  - Press clippings, February 19-May 30, 2010 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
  - Press clippings, June 18-September 12, 2010 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
  - Press clippings, February 11-June 12, 2011 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
  - Press clippings, September 30, 2010-January 16, 2011, 2010-2011 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
  - Press clippings, July 8-October 16, 2011 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - Press clippings, October 28, 2011-January 15, 2012, 2011-2012 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
  - Press clippings, February 3-May 20, 2012 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
  - Press clippings, June 8-September 9, 2012 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
  - Press clippings, October 12, 2012-January 20, 2013, 2012-2013 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
  - Press clippings, 2010-2012 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)